Guide to the Hosmer Correspondence, 1849-1853
Department of Special Collections
Hosmer Correspondence,
1849-1853
Special Collections M0037
Hosmer, Charles; Hosmer, Edward
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Provenance:
Unknown source
Access Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note:
Charles and Edward Hosmer left their parents, brothers and sisters in Avon, New York in March 1849 for California, arriving in September 1849. Edward travelled around Cape Horn by boat while Charles went overland by wagon train. In San Francisco, they became commission merchants and were doing well until robbed by a partner and burned out of their store. In the fall of 1851 Charles returned to New York to proceed with litigation against the partner. Edward went prospecting in the Feather River area but was unsuccessful.
Scope and Contents Note:
Collection consists of original and typescript copies of the letters of Charles and Edward Hosmer to their family in New York. The letters describe Charles' overland trip by wagon train and Edward's trip around Cape Horn to California, their work in San Franciso, and Edward's unsuccessful prospecting in the Feather River area. Also of note are the descriptions of early San Francisco including the people, business houses, shipping, and the weather. The collection also includes research notes.
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Container List
- Edward to father, New York, 1849 February 25, 1 (Box 1)
- Edward to father, New York, 1849 March 2, 2 (Box 1)
- Edward to father, New York, 1849 March 5, 3 (Box 1)
- Edward to brother, New York, 1849 March 5, 4 (Box 1)
- Edward to father, "at sea," 1849 March 8, 5 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, Illinois River, Peru, 1849 April 23, 6 (Box 1)
- Charles to father, St. Louis, 1849 April 26, 7 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, Missouri River, 1849 May 2, continued "on the Sacremento" 1849 May 5, Indian Territory, 8 (Box 1)
- Edward to parents, South America Valparaiso, 1849 June 16, 9 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, Great Salt Lake Valley, 1849 July 18, 10 (Box 1)
- Edward to father, San Francisco, 1849 September 25, 11 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1849 September 27, 12 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1849 October 31, 13 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1849 November 14, 14 (Box 1)
- Charles and Edward to parents, San Francisco, 1849 December 30, 15 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1850 January 8, 16 (Box 1)
- Charles and Edward to parents, San Francisco, 1850 January 31, 17 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1850 February 26, 18 (Box 1)
- Charles to parents, San Francisco, 1850 March 30, Easter Sunday, 19 (Box 1)
- Charles and Edward to parents, San Francisco, 1850 April 20, 20 (Box 1)
- John Pearson to George Hosmer, San Francisco, 1850 April 29, 21 (Box 1)
- Charles to "Brother Geo.," San Francisco, 1850 June 1, 22 (Box 1)
- Charles to "Home and Friends," San Francisco, 1850 June 30, 23 (Box 1)
- Charles to father, San Francisco, 1850 July 12, 24 (Box 1)
- Charles and Edward to father, San Francisco, 1850 July 28, 25 (Box 1)
- Edward to parents, San Francisco, 1850 September 1, 26 (Box 1)
- Charles to "Home," San Francisco, 1850 October 30, 27 (Box 1)
- Edward to "Parents, Brothers and Sisters," East Fork of the North Fork, Feather River, California, 1851 July 6, 28 (Box 1)
- Edward to "Home," Middle Fork, Dry Creek, 1 mile from Fiddletown, 1851 November 2, 29 (Box 1)
- Edward to parents, Dry Creek, 1852 January 10, 30 (Box 1)
- Edward to "Brother" (Charles), San Francisco, 1852 February 22, 31 (Box 1)
- Edward to "Parents and all at home," Junction Camp Woods, Tuwolumne County, California, 1853 February 6, 32 (Box 1)
- Typed copies of the original letters, 33 (Box 1)
- Research notes, 34 (Box 1)